A Guide to the Records of the Arlington Committee on Jamestown 2007, 2001-2008
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Records of the Arlington Committee on Jamestown 2007, 2001-2008
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
RG 174
7 boxes.
Arlington Committee on Jamestown 2007
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Joan McDermott, Chair of the Committee, in February 2009.
Historical Information
According to the final report to the Arlington County Board, the Board appointed an 18-member committee in October 2005, charged with planning events and legacy projects to commemorate the 400th anniversary of the founding of Jamestown in 1607. The chair was Joan McDermott. The first meeting was in November 2005, followed by monthly meetings. The committee planned and sponsored 40 events, activities, and projects during the period from May 1, 2006 and December 31, 2007. This was one of 181 programs in Virginia for this commemoration. The goals were to increase tourism, expand economic development, renew awareness of Virginia history, highlight local historical and cultural interests, and to involve local people in planned events.
Scope and Content
Record Group 174 measures approximately four linear feet of records dating from 2001 to 2008. Materials consist of minutes, correspondence, alphabetical files chiefly concerning activities and projects for the celebration, reports about the economic impact of the celebration on Arlington and the final report to the county board, grant proposals, promotional materials, magazine articles, clippings, and photographs, the majority from 2001 and from 2006 and 2007. They deal chiefly with the Jamestown 2007 celebration in Arlington, Virginia. Among the 40 events and activities described in detail are: staffing a booth at the Arlington County Fair, showing documentary films, sponsoring a play about Jamestown, holding author lectures, participating in two Jamestown Oak tree plantings, holding a book fair, and taking part in the Smithsonian Folklife Festival. There were three legacy projects: a heritage calendar, oral histories from 37 Arlington residents of different heritages and ages, and small grants to groups for projects such as the Lustron House Documentation Project, the Potomac Overlook Park Heritage Program, the Taylor Rain Garden, and a Colonial Faire.
Also included is a photograph album showing the Arlington Bicentennial celebration in July, August, and October 2001. This album shows local and state dignitaries at the celebrations (e.g. Jay Fissette, John Millikin, James Moran) well as actors in a play portraying Arlington history, filling of a time capsule chest and a celebration at the Arlington County Fair. Close to half of the record group consists of alphabetical files concerning planning for and execution of events for the celebration.
Arrangement
The record group is arranged into seven series by type of material. Series 1 contains minutes of the Arlington Committee on Jamestown 2007 with a small amount of related correspondence in chronological order. This series was constructed by the processor. Series 2 consists of 131 alphabetical files with titles retained from the folders as they arrived at the library. The folders arrived in rough alphabetical order in sections of two boxes but appeared to be part of one group with similar handwritten titles so were placed in the same series.
Series 3 consists of grant proposals to the committee for the celebration, most of which were funded and are noted in the Scope and Content section, and promotional materials such as the official commemorative publication and guides for local communities with suggestions for activities. Series 4 contains reports of the economic impact of the celebration and the Committee's final report. Series 5 contains magazine articles about the celebration in Virginia and the importance of the settlement for the country. Series 6 contains photocopies of clippings about the celebration.
Series 7 contains one photo of the Committee and one folder showing period-costumed Arlingtonians, as well as nine folders of Arlington Bicentennial photographs from the original 2001 album: July 26, August 16, September 21, and October 28. The album was disassembled and put in folders by date and photographic roll number as indicated in the album.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Jamestown Settlement -- Anniversaries, etc.; Jamestown Settlement -- Centennial celebrations, etc.; Jamestown (Va.); Arlington (Va.); Arlington County (Va.)
Contents List
- Minutes and Correspondence of the Committee
  - September-December 2005 (Box 1)
  - January-March 2006 (Box 1)
  - April-September 2006 (Box 1)
  - Regional Meeting Minutes, September 28, 2006 (Box 1)
  - October 2006-January 2007 (Box 1)
  - February-May 2007 (Box 1)
  - June-October 2007 (Box 1)
  - Regional Meeting Minutes, October 23, 2007 (Box 1)
  - November 2007-January 2008 (Box 1)
- Alphabetical Files
  - All Arlington Reads, 2006 (Box 1)
  - America's Anniversary Garden, 2005-2007 (Box 1)
  - Amy Ritchie Emails, 2006 (Box 1)
  - Amy Ritchie Memos, 2007-2008 (Box 2)
  - Appropriations for Jamestown 2007, April 27, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Arlington Brown Bag Roundtable, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Arlington County Fair, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Arlington County Fair, 2007 (Box 2)
  - Arlington Historical Society Article, 2006-2007 (Box 2)
  - Arlington Historical Society Article by Nancy Hall, 2007 (Box 2)
  - Arlington Historical Society Article re: 350th Anniversary by George Schnabel, 1957 (Box 2)
  - Arlingtones, 2006-2007 (Box 2)
  - Author Programs, 2007 (Box 2)
  - Barnes and Noble Fundraiser, 2006-2007 (Box 2)
  - Bluemont Junction Caboose, 2007 (Box 2)
  - Books on Jamestown, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Budget Hearing, County Board, March, May, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Cachet Contest, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Captain John Smith 1608 Event, 2007 (Box 2)
  - Captain John Smith Chesapeake National Historic Water Trail, 2006, 2007 (Box 2)
  - Charlie Clark Article - Capt. John Smith for AHS Magazine, [2007] (Box 2)
  - Children's Authors Programs, March 31, 2007 (Box 2)
  - Colonial Faire (Hesperus), 2007 (Box 2)
  - Commemorative Coin Program, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Commemorative Programs Jamestown 2007, 2007 (Box 2)
  - Committee - Jamestown 2006, 2006-2007 (Box 2)
  - Community Program Report, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Costumes, Jamestown 2007, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Costumes Policy, 2007 (Box 2)
  - County Board, April 26, 2006 (Joan McDermott) (Box 2)
  - Creative Projects - Encore Stage "The Jamestown Adventure", 2006 (Box 2)
  - Economic Impact Report, 2007 (Box 2)
  - Email List, 2007 (Box 2)
  - Emails from Joan McDermott, August 29, 2006 (Box 2)
  - English Commemoration, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Entertainment Jamestown 2007, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Environmental Initiative, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Fair Display, 2006-2008 (Box 2)
  - Final Report - Drafts and Notes, 2008 (Box 2)
  - Final Report to County Board, 2008 January-February (Box 3)
  - Final Report - State, 2007-2008 (Box 3)
  - Finance, 2007-2008 (Box 3)
  - Finance - Trust and Agency Account, 2007-2008 (Box 3)
  - Folklife Festival, 2007 June-July (Box 3)
  - FOIA Request, March-May 2007 (Box 3)
  - Funding Requests, January 2007 (Box 3)
  - Funding Requests - Detail (Box 3)
  - Godspeed Festival, March-June 2006 (Box 3)
  - Godspeed Festival - Alexandria, March-May 2006 (Box 3)
  - HB Woodlawn Volunteer Fair, November 13, 2007 (Box 3)
  - Heritage Calendar - 2007, 2006-2007 (Box 3)
  - History Club - YHS, 2006 (Box 3)
  - Indian Tribes - Federal Recognition of Virginia Tribes, April 2007 (Box 3)
  - Industry in Jamestown, 1607-1609, Workshop, June 13, 2007 (Box 3)
  - Jamestown 2007 Annual Report, 2007 (Box 3)
  - Jamestown ARticle in New Yorker, April 7, 2007 (Box 3)
  - Jamestown in APS Curriculum, 2002-2007 (Box 3)
  - Jamestown Inventory, 2007 (Box 3)
  - Jamestown Live! October 2006 (Box 3)
  - Jamestown 2007 Open House, 2006 (Box 3)
  - Jamestown Oak Planting, 2007 (Box 3)
  - JYF Programs, April 2, April 23, 2007 (Box 3)
  - JYF Outreach in Schools, 2007 (Box 3)
  - Jenny Dean Park/Talmadge Williams, May 2007 (Box 3)
  - Legacy Project, 2006 (Box 3)
  - Legislative Priorities - 2008 General Assembly (Box 3)
  - Letter to the Editor - Jamestown Elementary School, May 14, 2007 (Box 3)
  - Letterhead, Jamestown 2007 (Box 3)
  - Library Reservations, 2006 (Box 3)
  - Lustron Documentation Project, 2006 (Box 3)
  - Lustron Showcase, December 10, 2007 (Box 3)
  - LWV Annual Meeting, May 5, 2007 (Box 3)
  - Maps [ca. 2007] (Box 3)
  - March to Victory - W3R (Yorktown) September 23, 2006 (Box 3)
  - May 1 Event, March-May, 2007 (Box 3)
  - Meeting Place Memo, J2007, December 19, 2006 (Box 3)
  - Merchandise, 2006 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 2006-2007 (Box 3)
  - Musical Program, Jamestown 2007 2006 (Box 3)
  - Nauck Community Heritage Project, 2007 (Box 3)
  - Neighborhood Day Parade, 2006 May (Box 4)
  - The New World, January 28, 2007 (Box 4)
  - North Tract - Tom Dickinson (Box 4)
  - November 19, 2006 Film (Box 4)
  - Panels for Library - March-April 2007 (Box 4)
  - Stephen Patrick, August-November 2007 (Box 4)
  - Oral History - American Indian Interviews, 2008 (Box 4)
  - Oral History Project, 2006-2008 (Box 4)
  - Oral History Project Manager - Nancy Hall, 2006 (Box 4)
  - Potomac Overlook Heritage Program, 1989, 2007 (Box 4)
  - Potomac Overlook Regional Park - REsearch - Mary Schockley (Box 4)
  - David Price Lecture, February 26, 2007 (Box 4)
  - Proclamation, May 13, 2007 (Box 4)
  - Programs, November 8, 21, 2007 (Box 4)
  - Programs (Possible), 2006 (Box 4)
  - Project Acorn, 2007 (Box 4)
  - Project Acorn - Jamestown Oaks, 2007 (Box 4)
  - Project Proposal Guidelines and Comments, 2006-2007 (Box 4)
  - Promotion Plan, 2007 (Box 4)
  - Publicity, 2006 (Box 4)
  - Quiz - Jamestown 2007, 2007 (Box 4)
  - Rain Garden - Tayler E.S., May 2007 (Box 4)
  - Regional Meeting - NVA, September 2006 (Box 4)
  - Remarks, 2007 (Box 4)
  - Report to County Board, January 30, 2007 (Box 4)
  - Request for Funding: Art Installation and Play, Bluemont Junction Display, April 2006 (Box 4)
  - Saegmuller School Marker, 2007 (Box 4)
  - SCAN Donation, October 2006 (Box 4)
  - Schedule of Events, 2007 (Box 4)
  - School Board Presentation, September 2006 (Box 4)
  - Shallop, 2007 (Box 5)
  - Small Ships Event (Box 5)
  - Paul D. Snodgrass Information, May 2007 (Box 5)
  - Speaker List Jamestown 2007, 200 (Box 5)
  - St. Agnes Assembly, May 2007 (Box 5)
  - Stamps - Jamestown Cachets, May 2007 (Box 5)
  - Thank You Letter and Certificate, February 2008 (Box 5)
  - Time Capsule Dedication Ceremony and Thank You Reception, March 6, 2008 (Box 5)
  - Tom Dickinson Legacy Project, 2007 (Box 5)
  - Travel, 2006 (Box 5)
  - Trees - Notable Trees Nomination Form (Box 5)
  - Trip to Jamestown, November 3, 2007 (Box 5)
  - Virginia Diversity Garden, 2007 (Box 5)
  - Virginia Indian Heritage Program - Suggested Resources (Box 5)
  - Virginia Museum of Fine Arts Exhibit - Jamestown and Beyond (Box 5)
  - Virginia Museum of Fine Arts Traveling Exhibits, 2006-2007 (Box 5)
  - Volunteers, 2006-2007 (Box 5)
  - Walk, April 28, 2007 - Kevin Vincent (Box 5)
  - Website, 2006-2007 (Box 5)
  - Whole Foods Donation, 2007 (Box 5)
  - Karenne Wood, December 3, 2007 Program, 2007 (Box 5)
- Grant Proposals and Promotional Materials
  - Grant Proposals, 2007 (Box 5)
  - Official Commemorative Publication, 2007 (Box 5)
  - Virgia 2007 Community Program/Media Sponsorship Guide, 2007 (Box 5)
  - Jamestown Celebration Promotional Portfolios, 2007 (Box 5)
  - Jamestown Celebration Brochures and Flyers, 2007 (1) (Box 5)
  - Jamestown Celebration Brochures and Flyers, 2007 (2) (Box 6)
  - Maps, Calendars, Bookmarks, Decals, 2007 (Box 6)
  - Posters and Bookplates, 2007 (Box 6)
- Reports, including Final Report
  - Economic Impact Analysis, 2008 (Box 6)
  - Final Report of the Arlington Committee on Jamestown 2007 Community Program (Box 6)
- Magazine Articles
  - Arlington Connection, 2006 (Box 6)
  - Arlington Historical Magazine, 2006-2007 (Box 6)
  - Heritage Travel, 2007 (Box 6)
  - Preservation, 2007 (Box 6)
  - Rosslyn, 2007 (Box 6)
  - Save the Bay, 2007 (Box 6)
  - Shipmates, 2006-2007 (Box 6)
  - Smithsonian (Box 6)
  - Time, 2007 (Box 6)
  - Virginia Secrets, 2005 (Box 6)
  - VEA News (Box 6)
  - National Parks, 2007 (Box 6)
  - VFH News, 2007 (Box 6)
- Clippings
  - Clippings (1) (Box 7)
  - Cliippings (2) (Box 7)
- Photographs from Arlington Bicentennial Album and Jamestown 2007 Celebration
  - Arlington Committee on Jamestown 2007 Photograph (Box 7)
  - Arlington Bicentennial Photograph Album Roll 1, July 26, 2001 (Box 7)
  - Arlington Bicentennial Photograph Album Roll 2, July 26, 2001 (Box 7)
  - Arlington Bicentennial Photograph Album Roll 3, July 26, 2001 (Box 7)
  - Arlington Bicentennial Photograph Album Roll 4, July 26, 2001 (Box 7)
  - Arlington Bicentennial Photograph Album Roll 1, September 21, 2001 (Box 7)
  - Arlington Bicentennial Photograph Album Roll 1, August 16, 2001 (Box 7)
  - Arlington Bicentennial Photograph Album Roll 2, August 16, 2001 (Box 7)
  - Arlington Bicentennial Photograph Album Roll 1, October 28, 2001 (Box 7)
  - Arlington Bicentennial Photograph Album Roll 2, October 28, 2001 (Box 7)
  - Copies of Photographs of Jamestown 2007 Celebration, 2007 (Box 7)